"Productivity is not everything, but in the long run,
"الإنتاجية ليست كل شيء، ولكن على المدى البعيد،
it is almost everything."
هى تقريباً كل شيء."
So this is serious.
إذاً الأمر جاد.
There are not that many things on earth that are "almost everything."
على الأرض، أشياء كثيرة لايمكن أن توصف تقريباً بأنها "كل شيء."
Productivity is the principal driver of the prosperity of a society.
الإنتاجية هي المحرك الرئيسي لإزدهار المجتمع،
So we have a problem.
لذلك لدينا مشكلة.
In the largest European economies,
فى الإقتصاديات الأوربية الكبرى،
productivity used to grow five percent per annum
اعتادت إنتاجياتها على نمو بمعدل 5% سنوياً
in the '50s, '60s, early '70s.
في الخمسينيات والستينيات وبداية السبعينيات.
From '73 to '83: three percent per annum.
من عام 73 حتى عام 83: كان النمو بمعدل 3% سنوياً.
From '83 to '95: two percent per annum.
من عام 83 حتى عام 95 : 2% سنوياً.
Since 1995: less than one percent per annum.
منذ 1995م : أقل من 1% سنوياً.
The same profile in Japan.
نفس الشيء فى اليابان.
The same profile in the US,
نفس الشيء في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
despite a momentary rebound 15 years ago,
رغم الإنتعاش المؤقت منذ 15 عاماً،
and despite all the technological innovations
ورغم كل الإختراعات التكنولوجية
around us: the Internet, the information,
من حولنا: ثورة الإنترنت والمعلومات
the new information and communication technologies.
والتكنولوجيات الجديدة للمعلومات والتواصل.
When productivity grows three percent per annum,
عندما تنمو الإنتاجية بمعدل 3% سنوياً،
you double the standard of living every generation.
فإنكم تضاعفون مستوى المعيشة لكل جيل.
Every generation is twice as well-off as its parents'.
بحيث يكون مستوى معيشة كل جيل ضعف مستوى معيشة والديه
When it grows one percent per annum,
عندما يكون معدل النمو 1% سنوياً،
it takes three generations to double the standard of living.
فإن الأمر يتطلب ثلاثة أجيال لمضاعفة مستوى المعيشة.
And in this process, many people will be less well-off than their parents.
وفى هذه العملية، سيكون مستوى معيشة العديد من الأشخاص أقل من مستوى أبائهم.
They will have less of everything:
كل شيء لديهم سيكون قليلاً:
smaller roofs, or perhaps no roof at all,
منازل صغيرة، أو ربما لا منازل أصلاً،
less access to education, to vitamins, to antibiotics, to vaccination --
قلة في التعليم، نقص في الفيتامينات والمضادات الحيوية واللقاحات الطبية--
to everything.
في كل شيء.
Think of all the problems that we're facing at the moment.
فكروا فى كل المشاكل التي نواجهها حالياً.
All.
كلها.
Chances are that they are rooted in the productivity crisis.
هناك احتمالات أنها متجذرة فى أزمة الإنتاجية.
Why this crisis?
لماذا هذه الأزمة؟
Because the basic tenets about efficiency --
لأن المبادئ الأساسية للكفاءة --
effectiveness in organizations, in management --
الفعالية في المنظمات وفي الإدارة --
have become counterproductive for human efforts.
أصبحت ذات آثار سلبية على الجهود البشرية.
Everywhere in public services -- in companies, in the way we work,
فى كل مكان في الخدمات العامة -- في الشركات، فى طريقة عملنا،
the way we innovate, invest -- try to learn to work better.
في الطريقة التي نخترع و نستثمر بها -- أو نحاول بها تعلم كيفية العمل بشكل أفضل.
Take the holy trinity of efficiency:
خذوا مثلاً الثالوث المقدس للكفاءة:
clarity, measurement, accountability.
الوضوح، القياس، المسؤولية،
They make human efforts derail.
إنها تعرقل الجهود البشرية.
There are two ways to look at it, to prove it.
وهناك طريقتين لدراستها وإثباتها.
One, the one I prefer,
أولاً، تلك التي أُفضل،
is rigorous, elegant, nice -- math.
وهي دقيقة وأنيقة وجميلة -- الرياضيات.
But the full math version takes a little while,
لكن النسخة الرياضية تتطلب بعض الوقت لشرحها،
so there is another one.
لذا هناك طريقة أخرى لشرحها.
It is to look at a relay race.
وهي سباق التتابع.
This is what we will do today.
هذا ما سنفعله اليوم.
It's a bit more animated, more visual and also faster -- it's a race.
سيكون الأمر حيوي وبصري وسريع بعض الشيء -- إنه سباق.
Hopefully, it's faster.
ونأمل أن يكون سريعاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
World championship final -- women.
نهائي بطولة العالم -- نساء.
Eight teams in the final.
ثمان منتخبات في النهائي.
The fastest team is the US team.
منتخب الولايات المتحدة هو الأسرع بينها.
They have the fastest women on earth.
يملكون أسرع نساء في الأرض.
They are the favorite team to win.
وهن الأوفر حظاً للفوز.
Notably, if you compare them to an average team,
ولاسيما إذا قارنتموهن بمنتخب متوسط،
say, the French team,
فلنقل، المنتخب الفرنسي،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
based on their best performances in the 100-meter race,
استناداً إلى أفضل نتائجهن في سباق 100م ،
if you add the individual times of the US runners,
وإذا أضفتم عليها التوقيت الفردي لمتسابقات الولايات المتحدة،
they arrive at the finish line 3.2 meters ahead of the French team.
حيث يقطعن خط النهاية 3,2 متر أمام المنتخب الفرنسي.
And this year, the US team is in great shape.
وفي هذه السنة، يتمتع المنتخب الأمريكي بلياقة بدنية رائعة.
Based on their best performance this year,
واستناداً إلى نتائجهن لهذه السنة،
they arrive 6.4 meters ahead of the French team,
فإنهن سيقطعن خط النهاية 6,4 متر أمام المنتخب الفرنسي،
based on the data.
وذلك استناداً إلى البيانات.
We are going to look at the race.
سنشاهد الآن تسجيلاً لسباق الجري.
At some point you will see, towards the end,
خلال السباق وقبل النهاية ستشاهدون
that Torri Edwards, the fourth US runner, is ahead.
بأن توري ادواردز المتسابقة الرابعة للمنتخب الأمريكي متقدمة.
Not surprising -- this year she got the gold medal in the 100-meter race.
ليست مفاجئة -- فقد حصلت هذه السنة على الميدالية الذهبية لسباق 100م.
And by the way, Chryste Gaines, the second runner in the US team,
وبالمناسبة فإن كريستي جينز، المتسابقة الثانية بالمنتخب الأمريكي
is the fastest woman on earth.
هي أسرع امرأة على الأرض.
So, there are 3.5 billion women on earth.
تخيلوا، من بين 3,5 مليار امرأة على الأرض.
Where are the two fastest? On the US team.
أين توجد أسرع امرأتين في العالم؟ في المنتخب الأمريكي
And the two other runners on the US team are not bad, either.
كما أن مستوى المتسابقتين الأخريين مع المنتخب الأمريكي ليستا سيئتين أيضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So clearly, the US team has won the war for talent.
بصراحة، المنتخب الأمريكي فاز بحرب الموهبة.
But behind, the average team is trying to catch up.
لكن في الخلف، يحاول المنتخب المتوسط اللحاق به.
Let's watch the race.
دعونا نشاهد السباق.
(Video: French sportscasters narrate race)
(فيديو: الصحفيين الفرنسيين المعلقين على السباق)
(Video: Race narration ends)
(فيديو: نهاية التعليق على السباق)
Yves Morieux: So what happened?
إيف موريو: ما الذي حدث؟
The fastest team did not win; the slower one did.
خسر أسرع منتخب وفاز الأبطأ.
By the way, I hope you appreciate
بالمناسبة، أرجو أن تكون قد ثمنتم
the deep historical research I did to make the French look good.
البحث التاريخي العميق الذي قمت به لألمع صورة الفرنسيين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But let's not exaggerate -- it's not archeology, either.
لكن دعونا لا نبالغ -- فهو ليس تنقيب عن الآثار أيضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But why?
لكن لماذا؟
Because of cooperation.
بفضل التعاون.
When you hear this sentence:
عندما تسمعون هذه الجملة:
"Thanks to cooperation, the whole is worth more than the sum of the parts."
"بفضل التعاون، الكل أفضل من مجموع الجزء."
This is not poetry; this is not philosophy.
هذا ليس شعراً أو فلسفة.
This is math.
إنها الرياضيات.
Those who carry the baton are slower,
قد تكون المتسابقات اللواتي يحملن العصا بطيئات،
but their baton is faster.
لكن عصاهن هي الأسرع.
Miracle of cooperation:
معجزة التعاون:
it multiplies energy, intelligence in human efforts.
تضاعف طاقة وكفاءة الجهود البشرية.
It is the essence of human efforts:
إنه جوهر الجهود البشرية:
how we work together, how each effort contributes to the efforts of others.
كيف نعمل معاً، وكيف يساهم كل جهد في دعم جهود الأخرين.
With cooperation, we can do more with less.
بفضل التعاون، يمكننا تحقيق الكثير بالقليل.
Now, what happens to cooperation when the holy grail --
الآن، ماذا يحدث للتعاون عند ظهور الكأس المقدس؟
the holy trinity, even --
الثالوث المقدس، إن أردتم --
of clarity, measurement, accountability --
الوضوح، القياس، المسؤولية،
Clarity.
الوضوح.
Management reports are full of complaints about the lack of clarity.
التقارير الإدارية مليئة بالتذمر من نقص الوضوح.
Compliance audits, consultants' diagnostics.
وكذا الحال في تدقيق الحسابات والتشخيصات الاستشارية.
We need more clarity, we need to clarify the roles, the processes.
نحتاج مزيداً من الوضوح وتوضيح أكبر للأدوار والعمليات.
It is as though the runners on the team were saying,
وكأن العداؤون بالفريق يقولون:
"Let's be clear -- where does my role really start and end?
"دعونا نكون أوضح - أين يبدأ دوري وأين ينتهي؟
Am I supposed to run for 95 meters, 96, 97...?"
هل عليِّ أن أجري مسافة 95 متراً أو 96 أو 97...؟"
It's important, let's be clear.
هذا مهم، دعونا نكون أوضح.
If you say 97, after 97 meters,
إن قلتم المسافة 97 متر تتابع،
people will drop the baton, whether there is someone to take it or not.
فإن العداؤون سيسلمون العصا سواء أكان هناك أحد لأخذها أم لا.
Accountability.
المسؤولية.
We are constantly trying to put accountability
نحاول دائماً إلقاء المسؤولية
in someone's hands.
على عاتق أحدٍ ما.
Who is accountable for this process?
من هو المسؤول عن هذه العملية؟
We need somebody accountable for this process.
نحتاج لشخص مسؤول من أجل هذه العملية.
So in the relay race, since passing the baton is so important,
وفي سباق التتابع، بما أن تسليم العصا هو أمر مهم،
then we need somebody clearly accountable for passing the baton.
فإننا بحاجة إلى شخص مسؤول لتسليم العصا.
So between each runner,
لذا، بين كل عدائين،
now we will have a new dedicated athlete,
سيكون لدينا رياضي متخصص،
clearly dedicated to taking the baton from one runner,
في أخذ العصا من العداء الأول
and passing it to the next runner.
لتسليمها إلى العداء التالي.
And we will have at least two like that.
وسيكون لدينا على الأقل اثنين منهم.
Well, will we, in that case, win the race?
إذاً، هل سنفوز في هذه الحالة بالسباق؟
That I don't know, but for sure,
لا أدري، لكن الأكيد،
we would have a clear interface,
أنه سيكون لدينا واجهة واضحة،
a clear line of accountability.
خط مسؤولية واضح.
We will know who to blame.
سنعرف على من سنلقي اللوم.
But we'll never win the race.
لكننا لن نفوز أبداً بالسباق.
If you think about it, we pay more attention
إن فكرتم في ذلك، نحن نهتم أكثر
to knowing who to blame in case we fail,
بمعرفة من سنلوم في حال فشلنا،
than to creating the conditions to succeed.
بدلاً من خلق شروط النجاح.
All the human intelligence put in organization design --
كل الذكاء البشري وضع في تصميم المنظمات --
urban structures, processing systems --
البنايات الحضارية، أنظمة المعالجة --
what is the real goal?
وما هو الهدف الحقيقي؟
To have somebody guilty in case they fail.
الحصول على شخص للومه في حال الفشل.
We are creating organizations able to fail,
نحن نخلق منظمات قابلة للفشل،
but in a compliant way,
لكن وفقاً لقواعد
with somebody clearly accountable when we fail.
تجعل من شخص ما يبدو بوضوح أنه المسؤول حال الفشل.
And we are quite effective at that -- failing.
ونحن حقاً فعالين في هذا -- الفشل.
Measurement.
القياس.
What gets measured gets done.
ما أمكن قياسه أمكن إنجازه
Look, to pass the baton, you have to do it at the right time,
انظروا إلى تسليم العصا، عليكم القيام بذلك في الوقت المناسب،
in the right hand, at the right speed.
وإلى اليد، وبالسرعة المناسبتين.
But to do that, you have to put energy in your arm.
لكن للقيام بذلك، عليكم إرسال الطاقة إلى ذراعكم.
This energy that is in your arm will not be in your legs.
والطاقة التي أرسلت إلى ذراعك لن تكون في قدميك.
It will come at the expense of your measurable speed.
ستقلل من سرعتك المقاسة.
You have to shout early enough to the next runner
فعليك الصراخ أبكر بما يكفي نحو العداء التالي
when you will pass the baton, to signal that you are arriving,
عند تسليمك العصا، لتنبيه إلى وصولك،
so that the next runner can prepare, can anticipate.
ليتسنى للعداء التالي الوقت للاستعداد، حتى يأخذ دوره.
And you have to shout loud.
وعليك الصراخ بصوت عال.
But the blood, the energy that will be in your throat
لكن الدم والطاقة اللذين سيتدفقان نحو حنجرتك
will not be in your legs.
لن تكونا في قدميك.
Because you know, there are eight people shouting at the same time.
لأنكم تعرفون، أن هناك 8 أشخاص آخرين يصرخون في نفس الوقت.
So you have to recognize the voice of your colleague.
لذا عليك التعرف على صوت زميلك.
You cannot say, "Is it you?"
فلا مجال لأن تقولوا: "هل هذا أنت؟"
Too late!
سيفوتكم القطار!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, let's look at the race in slow motion,
لذا، دعونا نشاهد السباق بالعرض البطيء،
and concentrate on the third runner.
ولنركز على العداءة الثالثة.
Look at where she allocates her efforts,
لاحظوا أين توزع مجهوداتها،
her energy, her attention.
طاقتها، وتركيزها.
Not all in her legs -- that would be great for her own speed --
ليست مركزة بالكامل في قدميها -- ذلك سيكون جيداً لسرعتها --
but in also in her throat, arm, eye, brain.
لكن ركزت القليل أيضا في حنجرتها وذراعها وعينيها ودماغها.
That makes a difference in whose legs?
على من يؤثر ذلك؟
In the legs of the next runner.
على قدمي العداءة التالية.
But when the next runner runs super-fast,
لكن عندما انطلقت العداءة التالية مسرعة،
is it because she made a super effort,
هل كان بسبب أنها قامت بمجهود كبير،
or because of the way the third runner passed the baton?
أم بفضل طريقة تسيلم العداءة الثالثة للعصا؟
There is no metric on earth that will give us the answer.
لا يوجد على الأرض نظام متري يمكنه تقديم جواب
And if we reward people on the basis of their measurable performance,
وإن كافأنا الأشخاص بناء على قياسات فعاليتهم،
they will put their energy, their attention, their blood
سيوجهون طاقتهم وتركيزهم ودماءهم
in what can get measured -- in their legs.
في ما يمكن قياسه -- أي أقدامهم.
And the baton will fall and slow down.
والعصا ستسقط وتتباطأ
To cooperate is not a super effort,
التعاون لا يتطلب مجهود خارق،
it is how you allocate your effort.
بل كيفية توزيع مجهودكم.
It is to take a risk,
وهو المخاطرة،
because you sacrifice the ultimate protection
لأنكم تضحون بالحماية القصوى
granted by objectively measurable individual performance.
الذي تمنحه لكم فعاليتكم الفردية القابلة للقياس بموضوعية.
It is to make a super difference in the performance of others,
وهو أن نحدث فارق كبير بالمقارنة مع فعالية الأخرين،
with whom we are compared.
الذين نقارن بهم.
It takes being stupid to cooperate, then.
سيكون من الغباء التعاون معهم إذاً.
And people are not stupid; they don't cooperate.
والناس ليسوا بأغبياء؛ إنهم لا يريدون التعاون.
You know, clarity, accountability, measurement were OK
تعلمون: الوضوح، المسؤولية، القياس كانت قيم فعالة
when the world was simpler.
عندما كان العالم أبسط.
But business has become much more complex.
لكن أصبحت التجارة أكثر تعقيداً.
With my teams, we have measured
بمساعدة فريقي، قِسْنَا تطور
the evolution of complexity in business.
مستوى التعقيد في التجارة.
It is much more demanding today to attract and retain customers,
فمن الصعب اليوم جذب الزبائن والمحافظة عليهم،
to build advantage on a global scale,
أو بناء قدرات تجارية على المستوى العالمي،
to create value.
لخلق قيمة اقتصادية.
And the more business gets complex,
ومع ازدياد تعقيد التجارة،
the more, in the name of clarity, accountability, measurement
نطالب أكثر بالوضوح والمسؤولية والقياس،
we multiply structures, processes, systems.
فضاعفنا في عدد الأقسام والعمليات والأنظمة.
You know, this drive for clarity and accountability triggers
أتعلمون، هذه النزعة نحو الوضوح والمسؤولية
a counterproductive multiplication of interfaces, middle offices,
أدت إلى تعدد نتائج عكسية فأُنشئ على أثرها المكاتب الوسيطة
coordinators that do not only mobilize people and resources,
وجيء بالمنسقين الإداريين الذين لا يكتفون فقط بحشد الموظفين والموارد،
but that also add obstacles.
لكن أيضاً بإضافة المزيد من العقبات.
And the more complicated the organization,
وكلما كانت المنظمة معقدة،
the more difficult it is to understand what is really happening.
كلما زادت صعوبة فهم ما يحدث بالفعل.
So we need summaries, proxies, reports,
لذا نكون بحاجة إلى تقارير ووكلاء ومحاضر إدارية
key performance indicators, metrics.
ومؤشرات عن الكفاءة ومقاييس.
So people put their energy in what can get measured,
وبالتالي يصرف الناس طاقتهم في ما يمكن قياسه،
at the expense of cooperation.
على حساب التعاون.
And as performance deteriorates,
ومع تدهور الكفاءة،
we add even more structure, process, systems.
فنضيف المزيد من الأقسام والعمليات والأنظمة.
People spend their time in meetings,
فيقضي الناس وقتهم في الإجتماعات
writing reports they have to do, undo and redo.
وفي كتابة التقارير الملزمين بها، وتسلم أخرى والرد عليها...
Based on our analysis, teams in these organizations
واستناداً إلى تحليلنا، فإن مجموعات العمل في هذه المنظمات
spend between 40 and 80 percent of their time wasting their time,
تقضي مابين 40 و80% من وقتها في تضييع وقتها،
but working harder and harder, longer and longer,
لكن مع العمل بكد ولمدد أطول أكثر فأكثر،
on less and less value-adding activities.
مع أنشطة مضافة ذات قيم لكنها ضعيفة.
This is what is killing productivity,
وهذا هو ما يقتل الإنتاجية،
what makes people suffer at work.
وما يجعل الناس تعاني في العمل.
Our organizations are wasting human intelligence.
منظماتنا تبدد الذكاء البشري.
They have turned against human efforts.
لقد انقلبت ضد الجهود البشرية.
When people don't cooperate,
فعندما لا يتعاون الناس،
don't blame their mindsets, their mentalities, their personality --
لا تعتبوا على تفكيرهم أو عقلياتهم أو شخصياتهم --
look at the work situations.
انظروا إلى أوضاع العمل.
Is it really in their personal interest to cooperate or not,
هل هي حقاً تخدم مصالحهم الشخصية لتجعلهم يتعاونون أو العكس،
if, when they cooperate, they are individually worse off?
إن كان تعاونهم يجعلهم أسوأ على المستوى الفردي؟
Why would they cooperate?
فلماذا سيتعاونون؟
When we blame personalities
عندما نلوم شخصياتهم
instead of the clarity, the accountability, the measurement,
فبدلاً من الوضوح والمسؤولية والقياس،
we add injustice to ineffectiveness.
نضيف الظلم على انعدام الفعالية
We need to create organizations
نحن بحاجة لخلق منظمات
in which it becomes individually useful for people to cooperate.
يكون فيها التعاون مفيداً للناس على المستوى الفردي.
Remove the interfaces, the middle offices --
إلغاء الواجهات والمكاتب الوسيطة --
all these complicated coordination structures.
كل هذه الأقسام التنسيقية المعقدة.
Don't look for clarity; go for fuzziness.
فهي لا تقودكم إلى الوضوح؛ بل تذهب بكم نحو الغموض.
Fuzziness overlaps.
غموض متراكم.
Remove most of the quantitative metrics to assess performance.
ألغوا معظم المقاييس الكمية المستعملة لقياس الفعالية.
Speed the "what."
السرعة "ماذا."
Look at cooperation, the "how."
البحث عن التعاون، "كيف."
How did you pass the baton?
كيف تمررون العصا؟
Did you throw it, or did you pass it effectively?
هل ترمونها أم تمررونها بفعالية؟
Am I putting my energy in what can get measured --
هل أوجه طاقتي إلى ما يمكن قياسه --
my legs, my speed -- or in passing the baton?
قدماي، أي سرعتي -- أو إلى تمرير العصا؟
You, as leaders, as managers,
وأنتم بصفتكم كقادة، كمدراء،
are you making it individually useful for people to cooperate?
هل تجعلون الأمر مفيداً للناس على المستوى الفردي لكي يتعاونوا؟
The future of our organizations,
فمستقبل منظماتنا،
our companies, our societies
وشركاتنا ومجتمعاتنا
hinges on your answer to these questions.
متوقف على إجابتكم على هذه الأسئلة.
Thank you.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)